Finding Aid for Regional Transit Authority of Southeast Michigan records
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Regional Transit Authority of Southeast Michigan records 1945-2015 2001-2015
Regional Transit Authority of Southeast Michigan
2 linear feet
2015060 Bj
An agency tasked with overseeing the mass transportation operations of the Southeastern Michigan area. Records include local transit history, project plans, other regional research, and University of Detroit Mercy transit studies.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by the Regional Transit Authority of Southeast Michigan (donor no. 11334 ), in September, 2015.
The Regional Transit Authority (RTA) of Southeast Michigan is a 10 member board that was created by the Public Act No. 387 of 2012. The agency has jurisdiction over the mass transit operations of the Detroit area as well as Washtenaw, Oakland, Wayne, and Macomb counties. The RTA of Southeast Michigan also oversees other local transit agencies such as the Ann Arbor Area Transportation Authority and the Detroit Department of Transportation. The RTA of Southeast Michigan was predated by the Southeastern Michigan Transportation Authority in 1967. The RTA has completed projects such as the M1 Rail, new public transportation options in Detroit, as well as an increase in the amount of busses in the area.
The Regional Transit Authority (RTA) of Southeast Michigan records (2 linear feet and 24.8 MB) consist primarily of historical research and the project plans of the former transit agencies in the Southeastern Michigan region, arranged in alphabetical order. A large portion of the collection consists of material specifically relating to transit in the Metro Detroit area. These records consist of news clippings and brochures that document the publicity of some of the more recent RTA projects. Historical documents such as legislation and project plans predating the RTA are included as well. These were utilized as research materials for projects, as well as providing context for the other materials within the collection. A number of folders contain project plans for the M1 Rail and the Woodward Avenue Light Rail Transit Project. These materials document the implementation of new public transit systems in downtown Detroit, and contains records such as cost estimates and descriptions of the plans. The last of these Detroit related records are research materials from the transition period to Detroit Mayor Mike Duggan and his involvement in Detroit Department of Transportation (DDOT) plans during his tenure.
The other portion of the record collection consists of some regional research from other non-Michigan RTA areas, cities such as Atlanta, Cleveland, Denver, and St. Louis. These specific materials were referenced and utilized for the University of Detroit Mercy's transit studies, many of which are also contained within the collection. Some of these studies are contained within as paper copies, as well as digital versions, which can be downloaded online. The rest of the collection more directly correlates with the broader Southeast Michigan transit projects, including multi-year transportation plans compiled by the Southeastern Michigan Council of Governments. A small number of transit related legislation and policies for the state of Michigan are included, providing more context for some of the projects.
Subjects:
Buses--Michigan--Detroit.; Local transit--Michigan--Detroit.; Railroad cars--Michigan--Detroit.; Regional Transit Authority of Southeast Michigan.; Transportation--Colorado--Denver.; Transportation--Georgia--Atlanta.; Transportation--Michigan--Detroit.; Transportation--Missouri--St. Louis.; Transportation--Ohio--Cleveland.; Digital file formats.
Contributors:
University of Detroit Mercy.
Genre Terms:
Digital file formats.
- Regional Transit Authority of Southeast Michigan records
  - Detroit Transit
    - Brochures and news clippings, 2013-2014 (Box 1)
    - History, 1945, 2001-2011, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Project Plans, 1945, 2011-2015, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Research, 2013 (Box 1)
  - Regional Transit Research
    - Atlanta, 2006-2012 (Box 1)
    - Cleveland, 2006 (Box 1)
    - Denver, 2012 (Box 1)
    - St. Louis, 2002-2013, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Various, 2010-2013, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Southeast Michigan Regional Transit Plan, 1975-2008 (Box 2)
  - Transit Policies, 2003-2008, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - University of Detroit Mercy Transit Studies, 2013-2014 (Box 2)
  - University of Detroit Mercy Transit Studies (.ZIP file), 2014
Related Material
The Bentley Historical Library has a map of 1972 proposed transit routes from the Southeastern Michigan Transportation Association "Proposed Transit Routes, Southeast Michign Region." Records of the more recent and ongoing projects from the Regional Transit Authority of Southeast can be found on their website (http://www.rtamichigan.org/).